<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-17T12:14:31-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FilmFrameFocus</title><subtitle>Diary of a film worker</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Narrative Sovereignty</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/14/narrative-sovereignty.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narrative Sovereignty" /><published>2021-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/14/narrative-sovereignty</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/14/narrative-sovereignty.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="narrative-sovereignty">Narrative Sovereignty</h1>

<p>While most of the world was still fighting the pandemic, Africa had a much-overlooked plague of locusts descending on it. This reflects a major problem with the rest of the world, as we often ignore the African continent as a whole while it’s still often portrayed as unruly and dangerous in media. African cinema in particular doesn’t get much attention due to the lack of distribution in our Euro-centric focus on international cinema.</p>

<p>It’s hard to summarize African cinema as a whole –especially with the stark contrasts between North Africa and Sub-Saharan Africa. Colonialism still has lasting effects on almost all of these countries.</p>

<p>In the late colonial period, Jean Rouch, as a French outsider, captured African voices at a time when Africans themselves were rarely behind the camera. His films like <em>Moi, un Noir</em> (1958) blur fiction and documentary in a style later coined as ethno-fiction. While some argue his work democratized cinematic perspective, others critique it as another form of colonial gaze –even if collaborative. He was working during the late colonial era, and the power dynamics of that time bleed into the way his subjects are viewed.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/t9gYnHenApU?si=I0Nei_xBMOVJvRpG" title="Mandabi - Trailer" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>In response to this imbalance, <em>Mandabi</em> (1968) by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ousmane_Semb%C3%A8ne">Ousmane Sembène</a> offered a landmark moment in post-colonial cinema. It was the first film shot in Wolof, directly addressing Senegalese audiences without any need for French sensibilities. Sembène had already made <em>Black Girl</em> (1966), but <em>Mandabi</em> was a critique of colonial bureaucracy, religion, and neocolonial attitudes while framed as a simple story about a man trying to cash a money order.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touki_Bouki">Touki Bouki</a>, directed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djibril_Diop_Mamb%C3%A9ty">Djibril Diop Mambéty</a>, burst onto the scene five years later, blending surrealism with post-colonial disillusionment. It didn’t attempt to correct the outsider’s view; it sidestepped it completely. Mambéty presented a fragmented narrative that mirrored the fragmented identity of his characters—young lovers caught between Dakar and the dream of Paris. Where Sembène taught, Mambéty questioned.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xaWmfqrQjU4?si=eyLus6SMz4nwgWwa" title="Touki Bouki - Trailer" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>In North Africa, Egyptian filmmaker <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youssef_Chahine">Youssef Chahine</a> was exploring his own society in <em>Cairo Station</em> (1958), a neorealist tragedy that centered around a disabled newspaper vendor. Chahine’s work is often left out of the conversation around African cinema, even though Egypt had one of the most prolific film industries in the world during the mid-20th century. <em>Cairo Station</em> is a reminder that African cinema can’t be pigeonholed—not by geography, style, or intent.</p>

<p>Fast forward to today, and we see Nigeria’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema_of_Nigeria">Nollywood</a> becoming one of the largest film industries in the world. Though often maligned for its speed and output, Nollywood represents an alternative production model. It doesn’t wait for validation. Films are made fast, on the cheap, and with wide domestic appeal. Streaming services have started to catch on, with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netflix_in_Nigeria">Netflix</a> distributing titles like <em>Lionheart</em> (2018), signaling a shift in how African cinema enters global consciousness.</p>

<p>Uganda’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Who_Killed_Captain_Alex%3F">Nabwana I.G.G.</a> might be a one-man cinematic revolution. With a computer cobbled together from spare parts, he and his Wakaliwood crew created <em>Who Killed Captain Alex?</em> (2010), a DIY action flick that went viral for its sheer energy and homemade special effects. It’s not polished, but it’s electric. Like Nollywood, Wakaliwood proves that resource constraints don’t limit creativity.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BymeLkZ7GqM?si=ri9IeiLrRyPtc_3b" title="Who Killed Captain Alex? (Official Trailer)" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>But African cinema isn’t just genre films or political allegory. <em>Talking About Trees</em> (2019), a Sudanese documentary by Suhaib Gasmelbari, follows four aging filmmakers as they try to reopen an abandoned movie theater. It’s a quiet elegy for what was lost to decades of censorship and military rule, but also a meditation on the endurance of art. It ends with silence—the same silence that greets so many African films never screened beyond their own borders.</p>

<p>So how do we talk about African cinema? We don’t. Not as a whole. We talk about Malian cinema, South African cinema, Tunisian cinema. We talk about directors and movements, not just nations. We resist the flattening gaze.</p>

<p>Africa is not a genre.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>Cairo Station</em> (1958)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0051390">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/cairo-station/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Mandabi</em> (1968)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0063268">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/mandabi/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Moi, un Noir</em> (1958)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0051942">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/moi-un-noir/">Letterboxd</a> ]</li>
  <li><em>Talking About Trees</em> (2019)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt9658178">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/talking-about-trees/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Touki Bouki</em> (1973)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0070820">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/touki-bouki/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Who Killed Captain Alex?</em> (2010)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1813757">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/who-killed-captain-alex/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Youssef Chahine<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0149631">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youssef_Chahine">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Djibril Diop Mambéty<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0228013">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djibril_Diop_Mamb%C3%A9ty">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Nabwana I.G.G.<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm4254419">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nabwana_I.G.G.">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Jean Rouch<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0745541">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Rouch">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Ousmane Sembène<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0783733">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ousmane_Semb%C3%A8ne">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema_of_Nigeria">Cinema of Nigeria</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netflix_in_Nigeria">Netflix in Nigeria</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Rouch">Jean Rouch</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talking_About_Trees_(film)">Talking About Trees</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema_of_Egypt">Cinema of Egypt</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Narrative Sovereignty]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art vs. Artifice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/09/21/art-vs-artifice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art vs. Artifice" /><published>2020-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/09/21/art-vs-artifice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/09/21/art-vs-artifice.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="art-vs-artifice">Art vs. Artifice</h1>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yn4rJLzv4Jk?si=fIyZWPGFdTIsbXFI" title="Symbiopsychotaxiplasm: Take One - Clip" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>In the Spring of 1968, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0337348">William Greaves</a> set out to make a film about filmmaking. He called it “a fragment of the Godhead which is made up of other Godhead fragments.” This movie became <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0296881">Symbiopsychotaxiplasm: Take One</a></em> (1968).</p>

<p>Symbiopsychotaxiplasm is a deconstruction of the filmic form. The basic elements of the cinema are based around the non-existence of apparent camera and sound equipment. Based on the Hollywood-Mosfilm model by which most films are created, filmmaking techniques are supposed to be invisible.</p>

<p>Greaves created a screen test for his actors and assigned three cameras to film the event. The first camera focuses on the actors and the scene. The second camera focuses on the first camera crew filming the actors. The third camera focuses on the first camera, second camera, and the actors –basically everything encompassed in the filmmaking process.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm_TitleCard.jpg" alt="Symbiopsychotaxiplasm Title Card" /></p>

<p>The point of view that Greaves holds on filmmaking is the film will tell itself. A director is “a person who gets his ego out of his own way, he is at best a collaborator and servant of nature… but who, paradoxically, firmly controls the conditions of spontaneity, theatricality, and drama on the set.” His attempts at creating a short narrative-transitive based scene in a largely narrative-intransitive film are his means of exposing the constructs of the scene and film as a storytelling medium. A documentary is based on the assumption that the events, people, and places exist and are presented by a reliable source. Here, Greaves exploration of the documentary is comparable to jazz. The assumption is that it is based on improvisation and spontaneity in filmmaking and that it does not come out of rehearsal and interference. At any point, the film could have been based in the created reality of fiction or the experienced reality of documentary.</p>

<p>The Symbiopsychotaxiplasm moment explores the idea of one of these two realities on film. Our perception of a film is the impression of a reality we have upon viewing, whether fiction against documentary or narrative against avant-garde. It is similar to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apparatus_theory">Basic Cinematographic Apparatus</a> (the impression of reality based on the recording of images and their reproduction to be projected) that Jean-Louis Baudry presented. Greaves attempts to present in Symbiopsychotaxiplasm the Basic Cinematographic Apparatus that “offers the subject perception ‘of a reality’ whose status seems similar to that of representations experienced as perception.”</p>

<p>Throughout the film, there are several moments at which the crew discusses the evolution of the filmmaking process. They film themselves without the director present, only to help document the process for the director later since he is also his own editor. These moments of reflection by the crew are all under the assumption that the director did not instigate their discussions or influence their moments of self-expression about the film.</p>

<p>When the film crew later confronts the director about the project and their own conflict and confusion, Greaves tells them, “It’s a circus with a better script.” He wants to improvise something that is better than the written screen test as a reflection of the ‘establishment’ and a representation of the counter-cultural sentiments in the US at the time. It is a “creative piece of cinematic experience” as Greaves divulges his own expectations to the crew following eight days of filming the same screen test repeatedly with occasionally different actors.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm_BillGreaves.jpeg" alt="Bill Greaves" /></p>

<p>This experiment in filmmaking took nearly 130,000 feet of 16mm film (or roughly 55 hours). A producer -impressed with Greave’s previous documentary work- funded the Symbiopsychotaxiplasm Operation. The producer told him to make whatever he wanted. With complete control over his project, Greaves could create a film without the limitations of having overbearing control of producers and investors. The film’s photography was finished in 1968, though it took three years to finish the editing before a print was struck in 1971. At that time, Greaves took it to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cannes_Film_Festival">Cannes Film Festival</a> where it was screened. The projectionist confused the reels of the film and the screened film was nearly indecipherable for the audience, losing most of any chance for it finding an audience.</p>

<p>The confusion of reels on an experimental film such as Symbiopsychotaxiplasm would ruin the point of a documentary exploring the concept of filmmaking. After editing 55 hours of footage down to 75 minutes, the apparent narrative structure of the film would be loss as it is an experiment in storytelling. The intended presentation was made in editing. As in the film itself, Greaves explores the film developing as it is shot based on idea and not story. The structure of the filmic narrative came from the filming and editing of an idea, not from the story, script, and overall pre-production process.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm/Symbiopsychotaxiplasm_Crew.jpeg" alt="Crew" /></p>

<p>Symbiopsychotaxiplasm is a learning experience. It is not only an attempt to capture a moment, whether reality or simulacrum of reality, that is essential in understanding film as a form. A film does not have to be entertaining by conventional means if it is interesting. A film can be intellectually stimulating as it attacks the viewer’s perception of film and still be a worthy experience for the film viewer.</p>

<p>Symbiopsychotaxiplasm can also be used to examine a breakdown of storytelling. The crew in one scene examines the possibility that at any point the director might be hiding on the other side of a wall directing them and their discussion of the process of making a film. They are discussing whether or not Greaves is controlling the theatricality of capturing reality and what is presented, as reality could very well be fiction.</p>

<p>A story is presented based on the assumption that it is either a documentary or fiction. The film is the reflection of the intended vision by the filmmaker. It could be the focus of the camera or the order in which it is edited that determines a vision if it is not already present in the screenplay or design. By blurring the line between reality and fiction, Greaves expressed an element of himself and the experimentation that he sought in creating this film. It is a reflection of an author with the contribution of the cast and crew. The director becomes the so-called ‘Godhead’ that Greaves believed his film represented as the crew became the ‘fragments of the Godhead.’</p>

<p>In the same year that William Greaves was making Symbiopsychotaxiplasm, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000419">Jean-Luc Godard</a> was working on his film One AM (1968) which pursued similar themes. Though Godard abandoned the film in postproduction, it paralleled Symbiopsychotaxiplasm as an approach to the filmic experience that Godard shot in Chicago. Both films were attempts at counter-cinema and Symbiopsychotaxiplasm can be compared to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Wollen">Peter Wollen</a>’s breakdown of the revolutionary countering elements that Godard used in his cinema of the late 1960s. They are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Narrative Transitivity / Narrative Intransitivity: The narrative is not transitive as it is built upon episodes of a screen test filmed repeatedly, sometimes with different actors and intermittent moments of digression as Greaves plays the role of director and stops them in the acting exercise.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Identification / Estrangement: The characters are estranged from the audience, as they are breakdowns of characters themselves. The crewmembers are the only people to which identification can be found as they struggle to understand what is actually going on in the film alongside the audience.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Transparency / Foregrounding: The mechanics of filmmaking are visible throughout the film, foregrounding the fact that this is a movie and a not a suspension of disbelief.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Single Diegesis / Multiple Diegesis: The film presents multiple diegesis, as there are separate worlds for the film within the film and an overarching documentation of the separate worlds presented.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Closure / Aperture: The film is based on the idea that the audience understands the role of film and the crew apparent in the filmmaking process. This creates a world based on the intertextuality of not only referencing the filmmaking world, but also the process of interaction in presenting a reality of any sort.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pleasure / Unpleasure: The experience of the viewer in watching this film is not to be entertained, but to challenge the viewer in his/her perception of film and what is the actual reality presented.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fiction / Reality: The film is itself a questioning of fiction pitted against reality. At which point does the capturing of a reality become a representation of that reality or does it always become a representation of the filmmaker.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Symbiopsychotaxiplasm created its own counter-cinema model parallel to Godard. Godard would be the more cited individual in film history as he was already famous by the time he decided to pursue counter-cinema, breaking with the traditional filmmaking model of logical narrative progression. It was Greaves’ struggle and passion for filmmaking that led him to create a film such as Symbiopsychotaxiplasm: Take One.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Symbiopsychotaxiplasm: Take One (1968) [<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0296881/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/symbiopsychotaxiplasm-take-one/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Discovering William Greaves (2006) [<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt6676204/maindetails">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/discovering-william-greaves/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>William Greaves [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0337348">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Greaves">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Jean-Luc Godard [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000419">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Luc_Godard">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="reference">Reference</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apparatus_theory">Apparatus Theory</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cannes_Film_Festival">Cannes Film Festival</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="articles">Articles</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.criterion.com/current/posts/460-symbiopsychotaxiplasm-still-no-answers">Taubin, Amy. “Symbiopsychotaxiplasm: Still No Answers.” (2006). The Criterion Collection. 4 Dec. 2006.</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Baudry, Jean-Louis. “The Apparatus: Metapsychological Approaches To The Impression Of Reality In Cinema.” Film Theory And Criticism. Ed. Leo Braudy and Marshall Cohen. 7th ed. New York: Oxford UP, 2009. 171-88. Print.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Wollen, Peter. “Godard And Counter Cinema: Vent D’Est.” Film Theory And Criticism. Ed. Leo Braudy and Marshall Cohen. 7th ed. New York: Oxford UP, 2009. 418-26. Print.</p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Art vs. Artifice]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cinema’s Puppets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/08/25/cinemas-puppets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cinema’s Puppets" /><published>2020-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/08/25/cinemas-puppets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/08/25/cinemas-puppets.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="cinemas-puppets">Cinema’s Puppets</h1>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puppetry">Puppetry</a> has been an important part of cinema since the silent days. There are several types of puppetry and a variety of controls in their operation. There are physical manipulations such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hand_puppet">hand and rod puppetry</a>, but there are also more mechanical means such as cable control and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servomotor">servo motors</a>. These last two are what blur the line between puppets and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animatronics">animatronics</a>.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dCoqaaVD7-A" title="Puppet Show | Lili | Warner Archive" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>In <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/lili/">Lili</a></em> (1953), <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001989">Leslie Caron</a> plays a 16-year-old girl who gets entranced by a puppet show. When she should be working, she interacts with the puppets as if they are living, sentient beings. Even though Caron’s portrayal is to show her naivete, this captures an essential part of puppetry. Puppetry relies on the association of the real to make an audience believe in the movement of inanimate objects.</p>

<p>Since puppetry is a real time manipulation of objects, it can also loosely apply to the physical manipulation of people as seen in the Japanese film <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/double-suicide">Double Suicide</a></em> (1969).</p>
<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mzULuVYa6t0?si=CsDu7lPUMY_V__CJ" title="YouTube video player" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p><em>Double Suicide</em> is based on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunraku">bunraku</a> play <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Love_Suicides_at_Amijima">The Love Suicides at Amijima</a></em>. While <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0793983">Masahiro Shinoda</a> used actors in his story, the film begins with setting up a bunraku style puppet show and includes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuroko">kuroku</a> (stagehands dressed in all black) to manipulate the actors just as they would the puppets in a typical bunraku performance.</p>

<p>While most puppet related films had actors as the protagonists up to this point, once <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001345">Jim Henson</a> introduced his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Muppets">Muppets</a> to the world puppets could take the spotlight. Henson was always at the technological forefront for what could be done in puppetry, but it wasn’t until <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-dark-crystal/">The Dark Crystal</a></em> (1982) that his innovation caught up enough to be able to make an all encompassing puppet-based world for film.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CuqLsZ4qkNY" title="The Dark Crystal - Trailer" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>Undoubtedly, Jim Henson is the most influential figure in modern puppetry. <em>The Dark Crystal</em> became a cult classic after an initially poor run at the box office and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Henson's_Creature_Shop's_Creature_Shop">Jim Henson’s Creature Shop</a> is still a pre-eminent force in the creation of puppets and animatronics.</p>

<p>Beyond the influence of Henson, puppetry is otherwise relatively uncommon in films in the past few decades. There are a few great films that feature puppeteers such as <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-double-life-of-veronique/">The Double Life of Veronique</a></em> (1991) or <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-puppetmaster/">The Puppetmaster</a></em> (1993), but the most influential would probably be <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/being-john-malkovich/">Being John Malkovich</a></em> (1999). While the puppetry is seemingly based in satire, it also accurately shows what it’s like to be a puppeteer.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/25_F9irGdow" title="Being John Malkovich (10/11) Movie CLIP - John Malkovich Becomes a Puppeteer (1999) HD" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>As puppets and animatronics have mostly been replaced by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer-generated_imagery">CGI</a> in film in the past twenty years, there are still some interesting puppet-based works, primarily in short films. <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0378210">Heather Henson</a>’s <a href="https://www.handmadepuppetdreams.com/">Handmade Puppet Dreams</a> is a great resource for filmmakers embracing puppetry.</p>

<p>One feature film to come out of Handmade Puppet Dreams is <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/yamasong-march-of-the-hollows/">Yamasong: March of the Hollows</a></em> (2017). A visually stunning film that shows the possibilities of the medium on a limited budget.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3bvb4BDu0rM" title="Yamasong: March of the Hollows Official Trailer" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Being John Malkovich (1999) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120601/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/being-john-malkovich/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Dark Crystal (1982) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0083791/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-dark-crystal/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Double Life of Veronique (1991) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0101765/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-double-life-of-veronique/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Double Suicide (1969) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0064975/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/double-suicide/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Lili (1953) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0046000/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/lili/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Puppetmaster (1993) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0107157/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-puppetmaster/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Yamasong: March of the Hollows (2017) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt4191486/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/yamasong-march-of-the-hollows/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Heather Henson [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0378210">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heather_Henson">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Jim Henson [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001345">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Henson">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Masahiro Shinoda [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0793983">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masahiro_Shinoda">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="reference">Reference</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animatronics">Animatronics</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunraku">Bunraku</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer-generated_imagery">Computer Generated Imagery</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hand_puppet">Hand Puppet</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Henson's_Creature_Shop's_Creature_Shop">Jim Henson’s Creature Shop</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuroko">Kuroko</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Muppets">The Muppets</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puppetry">Puppetry</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servomotor">Servomotor</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cinema’s Puppets]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Smoke Gets in Your Eyes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/07/15/smoke-gets-in-your-eyes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Smoke Gets in Your Eyes" /><published>2020-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/07/15/smoke-gets-in-your-eyes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/07/15/smoke-gets-in-your-eyes.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="smoke-gets-in-your-eyes">Smoke Gets in Your Eyes</h1>

<p>After finally watching <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0459666/reference">The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant</a></em> (1972), I became fascinated by its first soundtrack choice: “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoke_Gets_in_Your_Eyes">Smoke Gets in Your Eyes</a>.”</p>

<p>Originally a 1933 show tune, it appeared in three films—<em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0026942/reference">Roberta</a></em> (1935), <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0039035/reference">Till the Clouds Roll By</a></em> (1946), and <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0044855/reference">Lovely to Look At</a></em> (1952)—before <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Platters">The Platters</a> recorded their famous 1958 version, which hit number one on the Billboard charts. Since then, The Platters’ cover has been featured in at least 24 movies, but <em>The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant</em> was the first to use it (in 1972).</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2WnTfjCEohs" title="The Platters - Smoke Gets in Your Eyes (from &quot;The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant&quot;)" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainer_Werner_Fassbinder">Rainer Werner Fassbinder</a> used it to illustrate the dynamic between Petra and her employee Marlene, injecting immediate romanticism yet hinting at the tension beneath the glamour.</p>

<p>Certain directors—<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenneth_Anger">Kenneth Anger</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Scorsese">Martin Scorsese</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quentin_Tarantino">Quentin Tarantino</a>—excel at using pop songs in film, often for contrast. “Smoke Gets in Your Eyes,” however, usually adds a touch of wistful romance.</p>

<p>The song’s first American film usage came from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Lucas">George Lucas</a> in <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/american-graffiti/">American Graffiti</a></em> (1973).</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j1q-QWHUU0g" title="American Graffiti (3/10) Movie CLIP - A Snowball Dance (1973) HD" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>Lucas staged a fight between <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Howard">Ron Howard</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cindy_Williams">Cindy Williams</a> against the sweet slow-dance backdrop, the song’s romantic veneer highlighting their drifting apart.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Spielberg">Steven Spielberg</a> used the same tune in <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/always/">Always</a></em> (1989) as a nostalgic reflection on Holly Hunter and Richard Dreyfuss’s relationship, turning it into a memory piece for his characters.</p>

<p>Similarly, in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema_of_Taiwan#New_Taiwanese_Cinema,_1982–1990">New Taiwanese Cinema</a> movement, both <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hou_Hsiao-hsien">Hou Hsiao-hsien</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Yang">Edward Yang</a> used “Smoke Gets in Your Eyes” in different ways. Edward Yang used it in <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-terrorizers/">The Terrorizers</a></em> (1986) to underscore loneliness, while Hou Hsiao-hsien opened <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/three-times/">Three Times</a></em> (2005) with the tune, establishing a nostalgic mood for his first story segment.</p>

<p>A pop standard can reinforce a film’s romantic themes or serve as a revealing counterpoint. “Smoke Gets in Your Eyes,” in particular, consistently carries a sense of bittersweet longing—making it a reliable choice for filmmakers seeking that emotional note.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>Always</em> (1989)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096794/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/always/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>American Graffiti</em> (1973)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0069704/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/american-graffiti/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>The Bitter Tears of Petra von Kant</em> (1972)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0068278/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-bitter-tears-of-petra-von-kant/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Lovely to Look At</em> (1952)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0044855/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/lovely-to-look-at/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Roberta</em> (1935)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0026942/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/roberta/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>The Terrorizers</em> (1986)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0091355/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-terrorizers/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Three Times</em> (2005)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0459666/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/three-times/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Till the Clouds Roll By</em> (1946)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0039035/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/till-the-clouds-roll-by/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Kenneth Anger<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001910">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenneth_Anger">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Rainer Werner Fassbinder<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001202">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainer_Werner_Fassbinder">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Hou Hsiao-hsien<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0396284/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hou_Hsiao-hsien">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Ron Howard<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000165">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Howard">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Holly Hunter<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000456">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holly_Hunter">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>George Lucas<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000184">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Lucas">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Martin Scorsese<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000217">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Scorsese">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Steven Spielberg<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000229">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Spielberg">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Quentin Tarantino<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000233">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quentin_Tarantino">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Cindy Williams<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0930286">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cindy_Williams">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Edward Yang<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0945981">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Yang">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema_of_Taiwan#New_Taiwanese_Cinema,_1982–1990">New Taiwanese Cinema</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Platters">The Platters</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoke_Gets_in_Your_Eyes">Smoke Gets in Your Eyes</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Smoke Gets in Your Eyes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Theatre on Film</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/06/10/theatre-on-film.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Theatre on Film" /><published>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/06/10/theatre-on-film</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/06/10/theatre-on-film.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="theatre-on-film">Theatre on Film</h1>

<p>Although <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatre">theatre</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film">film</a> share many similarities, they’re distinct experiences. Theatre can be narrative-based or more experiential, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spectacle">spectacle</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procession">pageantry</a>. Film can craft endless worlds with detailed sets or even venture into avant-garde territory.</p>

<p>Prominent stage shows are often filmed for cinema, though the result can be less than cinematic if not carefully planned. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingmar_Bergman">Ingmar Bergman</a>’s <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0072848/reference">The Magic Flute</a></em> (1975) is a landmark in filming an operatic performance in a way that feels alive on screen.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2yS9-9ic9A4" title="Ingmar Bergman's The Magic Flute - new trailer | BFI" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>One crucial difference between stage and screen is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Close-up">close-up</a>. Bergman’s film moves between behind-the-scenes shots and tight close-ups, immersing us in the theatrical setting while letting us see details that a live audience would miss.</p>

<p>The audience’s presence is integral to theatre; in film, realism often dominates. Polish avant-garde master <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tadeusz_Kantor">Tadeusz Kantor</a> presented <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0176266/">The Dead Class</a></em> (1977) as a performance recorded by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrzej_Wajda">Andrzej Wajda</a>. Wajda’s camera captures the intimate atmosphere of Kantor’s memory-laden, nihilistic stage piece. Though not literally on a proscenium stage, it retains the feel of a live performance.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aABFgNJOTZ4" title="Kantor La classe morta parte 1" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>By contrast, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Malle">Louis Malle</a>’s <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111590/reference">Vanya on 42nd Street</a></em> (1994) strips away most theatrical elements. The adaptation, directed by Malle from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andre_Gregory">Andre Gregory</a>’s workshop, is set in a dilapidated theater with no audience and minimal props. The cast rehearses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Chekhov">Chekhov</a>’s <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncle_Vanya">Uncle Vanya</a></em>, and we become the only audience. That layered approach underscores how a stage play’s essence can be preserved through close, thoughtful cinematography, even without typical sets or costumes.</p>

<p>All three works use a form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distancing_effect">Brechtian distancing</a> by revealing the artificiality of the stage. By “breaking the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_wall">fourth wall</a>” (or at least exposing it) and showing us the process, these films replicate aspects of live theatre’s interplay between performer and spectator. Filming a theatrical performance often requires more world-building than simply pointing a camera at the stage.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>The Magic Flute</em> (1975)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0072848/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-magic-flute/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Umarła klasa (The Dead Class)</em> (1977)<br />
[<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0176266/maindetails">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-dead-class/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Vanya on 42nd Street</em> (1994)<br />
[<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111590/maindetails">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/vanya-on-42nd-street/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Ingmar Bergman<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000005">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingmar_Bergman">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Bertolt Brecht<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0106517">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertolt_Brecht">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Anton Chekhov<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0155009">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Chekhov">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Andre Gregory<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0339737">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andre_Gregory">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Tadeusz Kantor<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm2207499">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tadeusz_Kantor">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Louis Malle<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001501">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Malle">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>David Mamet<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000519">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Mamet">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Andrzej Wajda<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0906667">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrzej_Wajda">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Close-up">Close-up</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composition_%28visual_arts%29">Composition</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distancing_effect">Distancing Effect</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dramaturgy">Dramaturgy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film">Film</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_stock">Film Stock</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_wall">Fourth Wall</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nihilism">Nihilism</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procession">Procession</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scenic_design">Scenic Design</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spectacle">Spectacle</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatre">Theatre</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncle_Vanya">Uncle Vanya</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worldbuilding">Worldbuilding</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Theatre on Film]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Blacklist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/05/16/the-blacklist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Blacklist" /><published>2020-05-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/05/16/the-blacklist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/05/16/the-blacklist.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-blacklist">The Blacklist</h1>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NdLuNtbSAck" title="Hollywood Stars In Communist Activities (1947)" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>Cinema is a powerful medium for communicating ideas. It can normalize perspectives and shape society. Any attempt to suppress free expression—whether by law or intimidation—threatens the arts. As America’s political divide widens, some fear a renewed stifling of speech. This evokes the era when the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC) targeted Hollywood, ultimately imprisoning ten men for refusing to cooperate in 1947.</p>

<p>During World War II, Hollywood was typically pro-military, backing the government’s efforts under President Franklin D. Roosevelt. But after the war, as power shifted in Congress, some of these same films were painted as “subversive” or “communist.” Under Republican leadership, HUAC’s Chairman J. Parnell Thomas declared “hundreds of…film people” were communist sympathizers, placing them on long lists. Some were labeled “friendly” for cooperating, but nineteen were declared “unfriendly.”</p>

<p>Those nineteen met at the home of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert_Biberman">Herbert Biberman</a> to plan their response. Most had been Communist Party members at some point, and ten were Jewish. This was likely not coincidental, considering HUAC’s focus on anti-communist rhetoric overlapping with suspicion of cultural others. Two 1947 movies on anti-Semitism, <em>Crossfire</em> (1947) and <em>Gentleman’s Agreement</em> (1947), also came under scrutiny.</p>

<p>In October 1947, the hearings began. “Friendly” witnesses included <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_L._Warner">Jack Warner</a> of Warner Bros. and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_B._Mayer">Louis B. Mayer</a> of MGM. Ironically, these men were also cited for producing “anti-American” films like <em>Mission to Moscow</em> (1943), which had been explicitly encouraged during the war. But HUAC seized on any link to the Roosevelt administration’s propaganda objectives.</p>

<p>After hearing from the so-called friendly witnesses, the committee turned to the “unfriendly” witnesses. Eleven testified:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Alvah Bessie</li>
  <li>Herbert Biberman</li>
  <li>Bertolt Brecht</li>
  <li>Lester Cole</li>
  <li>Edward Dmytryk</li>
  <li>Ring Lardner Jr.</li>
  <li>John Howard Lawson</li>
  <li>Albert Maltz</li>
  <li>Samuel Ornitz</li>
  <li>Adrian Scott</li>
  <li>Dalton Trumbo</li>
</ol>

<p>All had leftist leanings and had explored themes like anti-intolerance or social justice in their work. Chairman Thomas labeled these themes as communist.</p>

<p>Adrian Scott and Edward Dmytryk were summoned because of <em>Crossfire</em> (1947), a film fighting prejudice. It depicts a soldier who murders a Jewish man, pushing back against the then-common fear of addressing anti-Semitism on screen. <em>Crossfire</em> earned five Oscar nominations, but HUAC claimed it was subversive because it humanized a soldier’s vulnerability.</p>

<p><em>Action in the North Atlantic</em> (1943), written by John Howard Lawson and produced at the so-called “Roosevelt Studio” (Warner Bros.), also drew attention from HUAC. The film showed a convoy of equal allies delivering supplies to Russia, supporting the Soviet Union when it was America’s wartime ally.</p>

<p>Ten of the “unfriendly” witnesses refused to testify about their political affiliations, citing the First Amendment (not the Fifth). As a result, they were charged with contempt of Congress and became the “Hollywood Ten.” Most served prison time, and the studios—via the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldorf_Statement">Waldorf Statement</a>—agreed to blacklist them from employment. Some, like Edward Dmytryk, eventually returned to work; others, like Samuel Ornitz, never did.</p>

<p>The eleventh unfriendly witness was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertolt_Brecht">Bertolt Brecht</a>, who cooperated to avoid deportation under the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smith_Act">Alien Registration Act</a>. He left the U.S. shortly thereafter. HUAC had planned further investigations, but these initial hearings ended by late 1947.</p>

<p>This campaign effectively destroyed careers and chilled creative expression. Chairman Thomas claimed to protect America from communist influence but instead demonstrated how fragile free speech can be when fear rules.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mmeTKECkM2U" title="Victims of Hollywood's Blacklist" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>Action in the North Atlantic</em> (1943)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0035608">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/action-in-the-north-atlantic/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Battleship Potemkin</em> (1925)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0015648">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/battleship-potemkin/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Crossfire</em> (1947)<br />
[<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0039286/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/crossfire/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Hangmen Also Die!</em> (1943)<br />
[<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0035966/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/hangmen-also-die/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Mission To Moscow</em> (1943)<br />
[<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0036166/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/mission-to-moscow/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Alvah Bessie<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0078827">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alvah_Bessie">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Herbert Biberman<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0080868">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert_Biberman">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Bertolt Brecht<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0106517">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertolt_Brecht">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Lester Cole<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0170660">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lester_Cole">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Joseph E. Davies<br />
[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_E._Davies">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Edward Dmytryk<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0229424">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Dmytryk">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Ring Lardner Jr.<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0488057">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ring_Lardner_Jr.">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>John Howard Lawson<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0493251">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Howard_Lawson">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Albert Maltz<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0540816">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Maltz">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Louis B. Mayer<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0562454">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_B._Mayer">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Samuel Ornitz<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0650338">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Ornitz">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Adrian Scott<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0778789">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Scott">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>J. Parnell Thomas<br />
[<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._Parnell_Thomas">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Dalton Trumbo<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0874308">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalton_Trumbo">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Jack Warner<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0912491">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_L._Warner">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smith_Act">Alien Registration Act (Smith Act)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist_Party_USA">Communist Party USA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood_blacklist">Hollywood Blacklist</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_Un-American_Activities_Committee">House Un-American Activities Committee</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistance_in_the_Protectorate_of_Bohemia_and_Moravia">Resistance in the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Office_of_War_Information">United States Office of War Information</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldorf_Statement">Waldorf Statement</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="books">Books</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Ceplair, Larry. <em>Inquisition in Hollywood.</em> Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 2003.</li>
  <li>Dick, Bernard F. <em>Radical Innocence: A Critical Study of the Hollywood Ten.</em> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1989.</li>
  <li>Friedrich, Otto. <em>City of Nets: A Portrait of Hollywood in the 1940s.</em> Berkeley: University of California Press, 1997.</li>
  <li>McLaughlin, Robert L., and Sally E. Parry. <em>We’ll Always Have the Movies: American Cinema During World War II.</em> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 2006.</li>
  <li>Vaughn, Stephen. <em>Ronald Reagan in Hollywood.</em> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1994.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Blacklist]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Optical Printing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/04/28/optical-printing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optical Printing" /><published>2020-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/04/28/optical-printing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/04/28/optical-printing.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="optical-printing">Optical Printing</h1>

<p>While many filmmakers will commonly praise practical and optical effects, most modern <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_effects">visual effects</a> are created digitally. Digital is more efficient for time and money, allows for greater possibilities, and often creates impeccable images. The current craftsmanship of analog is often limited to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In-camera_effect">in-camera effects</a>, but many couldn’t have been accomplished in the past without the use of an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_printer">optical printer</a>.</p>

<p>Once an essential tool during post-production, the near forgotten <a href="https://cinefex.com/blog/optical-printer/">optical printer</a> is a device that can manipulate film footage by re-photographing each projected frame individually. This allowed for slight manipulations in the image to create <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_transition">transitions</a> and optical effects.</p>

<p>These effects created by the optical printer included:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frame_rate">Time Manipulation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissolve_\(filmmaking\)">Fade/Dissolve</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wipe_\(transition\)">Wipe</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Push-Off</li>
      <li>Vertical Movement</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superimposition">Superimposition</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Split_screen_\(video_production\)">Split-Screen</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matte_\(filmmaking\)">Mattes</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zooming_\(filmmaking\)">Optical Zoom</a></li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13b779a521ce05b02b31c9/1581141585958-FB2B6BDPFI3J9OXFYJWK/BladeRunner.jpg" alt="BladeRunner.jpg" /></p>

<p>When an optical printer is referenced, it is usually known as the device that effects pioneers such as Douglas Trumbull used on <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/2001-a-space-odyssey/"><em>2001: A Space Odyssey</em></a> (1968) or <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/blade-runner/"><em>Blade Runner</em></a> (1982). These visual effects were meant to be as invisible as possible so not to take you out of the story.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13b779a521ce05b02b31c9/1581445941059-125CIQZ7AJSR9O924LPS/Walkabout.jpg" alt="Walkabout.jpg" /></p>

<p>Other filmmakers used optical printers to add to the narrative. For <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_effect"><em>Walkabout</em></a> (1971), Nicolas Roeg utilized transitions and optical effects compounded with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photochemistry">lens flares</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camera_angle">camera angles</a> to give a sense of being in the Australian outback, giving weight to the narrative through visual storytelling while drawing attention to the techniques.</p>

<p>While there are still some uses for optical printers with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photochemistry">photochemical</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_preservation">film restorations</a>, the primary user base for the past few decades is comprised of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experimental_film">experimental filmmakers</a>.</p>

<p>Experimental filmmakers often work alone and must be competent as cinematographer, film lab, and editor to use an optical printer. One of the most famous experimental filmmakers was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_McLaren">Norm McLaren</a>. He won an Oscar for his short <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/neighbours/"><em>Neighbours</em></a> (1952), but his greatest work is arguably <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/pas-de-deux/"><em>Pas de deux</em></a> (1968).</p>

<p>The effects in <em>Pas de Deux</em> can easily be recreated in almost any <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-linear_editing_system">Non-Linear Editor</a> now. Digital effects allow for a quicker creation, but it doesn’t account for creative output. Working in a dark room with an optical printer, McLaren worked frame by frame, having to wait until the footage was processed at a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_laboratory">lab</a> to confirm that it turned out as he expected.</p>

<p>While Hollywood largely transitioned away from Optical Printing by the end of the 1980’s, experimental filmmakers continued to use these devices for their idiosyncratic works.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13b779a521ce05b02b31c9/1581449045892-GOAENHSNYY5W5V8TK0M7/TheHeartOfTheWorld.jpg" alt="TheHeartOfTheWorld.jpg" /></p>

<p><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-heart-of-the-world/">The Heart of the World</a> (2000) is often taught in film schools as an introduction to experimental film. Guy Maddin claimed the film couldn’t have turned out as expected <a href="https://guy-maddin.com/projects/the-heart-of-the-world/">without an optical printer</a>. Since then, Maddin has switched to mostly digital filmmaking, but the happy accidents that occurred in his earlier work can still be felt with every viewing, same as any other analog filmmaking.</p>

<p>There are so many more filmmakers that have utilized optical printing than what I’ve mentioned. Other notable filmmakers include to mention are <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0104132/">Stan Brakhage</a>, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0577263/">Jonas Mekas</a>, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0643171/">Nobuhiko Obayashi</a> (early work), <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0642271/">Pat O’Neill</a>, and <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0833247/">Chick Strand</a>, though the list goes on and on with many fascinating works.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>2001: A Space Odyssey (1968) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0062622/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/2001-a-space-odyssey/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Blade Runner (1982) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0083658/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/blade-runner/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Heart of the World (2000) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0260948/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-heart-of-the-world/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Neighbours (1955) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0044958/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/neighbours/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pas de Deux (1968) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0063417/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/pas-de-deux/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Walkabout (1971) [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0067959/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/walkabout/">Letterboxd</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Stan Brakhage [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0104132/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0833247/">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Guy Maddin [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0534665/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Maddin">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Norm McLaren [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0572235/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_McLaren">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Jonas Mekas [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0577263/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonas_Mekas">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nobuhiko Obayashi [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0643171/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobuhiko_Obayashi">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pat O’Neill [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0642271/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_O%27Neill_\(filmmaker\)">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nicolas Roeg [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001676/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Roeg">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Chick Strand [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0833247/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick_Strand">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Douglas Trumbull [<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0874320/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Trumbull">Wikipedia</a>]</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="reference">Reference</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camera_angle">Camera Angle</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissolve_\(filmmaking\)">Dissolve</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experimental_film">Experimental Film</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_laboratory">Film Laboratory</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_preservation">Film Preservation</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frame_rate">Frame Rate</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In-camera_effect">In-Camera Effects</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matte_\(filmmaking\)">Matte</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Film_Board_of_Canada">National Film Board of Canada</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-linear_editing_system">Non-Linear Editing System</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_printer">Optical Printer</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photochemistry">Photochemistry</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_effect">Special Effects</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Split_screen_\(video_production\)">Split Screen</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superimposition">Superimposition</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_transition">Transitions</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_effects">Visual Effects</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wipe_\(transition\)">Wipe</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zooming_\(filmmaking\)">Zooming</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="articles">Articles</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://nofilmschool.com/celluloid-saved">Celluloid Saved</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://guy-maddin.com/projects/the-heart-of-the-world/">The Heart of the World</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cinefex.com/blog/optical-printer/">O is for Optical Printer</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Optical Printing]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Panic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/23/dont-panic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Panic" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/23/dont-panic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/23/dont-panic.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="dont-panic">Don’t Panic</h1>

<p>In the midst of a crisis, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herd_mentality">herd mentality</a> tends to increase. <a href="https://www.vox.com/2020/3/11/21175987/trump-travel-ban-europe-coronavirus-speech">Certain media groups and politicians sow distrust</a>, causing <a href="https://laist.com/2020/03/10/coronavirus-fears-chinese-immigrants-guns.php">people to panic-buy supplies or even guns</a>. Cinema often explores the dangers of panic and groupthink.</p>

<p>One classic example is <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/panic/">Panique</a></em> (1947) by <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0245213/">Julien Duvivier</a> [corrected from “Claude Duvivier”]. An allegory for how the French could have supported Nazi occupiers, <em>Panique</em> realistically examines how people make decisions in a crowd that they would never make alone. When a man is accused of murder simply for being different, a small group’s vocal outrage eventually turns the entire town against him.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nXpddF9qBFA" title="PANIQUE - Trailer" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>While the remake, <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/monsieur-hire/">Monsieur Hire</a></em> (1989), is arguably more polished, <em>Panique</em> more directly addresses the danger of herd mentality in a contemporary post-WWII setting.</p>

<p>In Los Angeles, during the coronavirus outbreak, people scrambled for sanitary products and other items. LA is often stereotyped as morally or socially extreme; John Schlesinger’s <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-day-of-the-locust/">The Day of the Locust</a></em> (1975) took that idea to extremes, culminating in another frightening example of collective hysteria. During a movie premiere, tensions flare and a chaotic riot erupts when violence breaks out—yet radio commentators mistake the riot for excited moviegoers.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BQO5Xy2ebhs" title="The Burning of Los Angeles - The Day of the Locust (9/9) Movie CLIP (1975) HD" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p><em>The Day of the Locust</em> uses that riot to summarize its built-up anxieties. People easily succumb to fear, preparing for the worst once they sense any threat. Horror films often reveal the worst sides of humanity under pressure. In <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/ringu-0/">Ringu 0</a></em> (2000), the third in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ring_(franchise)">the Japanese “Ring” series</a>, Sadako’s curse stems from the fear she engenders in her theater troupe. As she’s blamed for strange occurrences, fear escalates to anger.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/khuxV85_7NI" title="Ring 0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<p>Fiction can be more “truthful” than reality in that it distills and focuses our anxieties. Hopefully, the real-world response to crises won’t match these movie scenarios—but these films remind us that panic can be as dangerous as any outbreak.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>The Day of the Locust</em> (1975)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0072848/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-day-of-the-locust/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Monsieur Hire</em> (1989)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0097904/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/monsieur-hire/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Panique</em> (1947)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0038824/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/panic/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Ringu 0</em> (2000)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0235712/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/ringu-0/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Julien Duvivier<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0245213/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julien_Duvivier">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronavirus_disease_2019">COVID-19</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herd_mentality">Herd Mentality</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ring_\(franchise\)">The Ring Franchise</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="articles">Articles</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://laist.com/2020/03/10/coronavirus-fears-chinese-immigrants-guns.php">“Coronavirus Fears Drive Chinese Immigrants to SGV Gun Shops,” <em>LAist</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2020/03/coronavirus-covid19-xenophobia-racism/607816/">“The Other Problematic Outbreak,” <em>The Atlantic</em></a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Don’t Panic]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In with the Old</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/04/in-with-the-old.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In with the Old" /><published>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/04/in-with-the-old</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/03/04/in-with-the-old.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="in-with-the-old">In with the Old</h1>

<p>A <a href="https://gizmodo.com/neural-networks-upscale-film-from-1896-to-4k-make-it-l-1841449875">video was posted to YouTube</a> today by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCD8J_xbbBuGobmw_N5ga3MA">Denis Shiryaev</a> showing how he used <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network">Neural Network AI</a> to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_scaler">upscale</a> historic footage, in this case <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-arrival-of-a-train-at-la-ciotat/">L’arrivée d’un train en gare de La Ciotat</a></em> (1896). While similar AI techniques recently gained attention through <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepfake">Deepfakes</a>, upscaling older footage has promising possibilities for film preservation—though it raises concerns about authenticity.</p>

<p>Personally, I love the idea of upscaling while still aiming for fidelity, but changing the framerate can resemble <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motion_interpolation">motion smoothing</a>, often clashing with a filmmaker’s intent. It reminds me of the controversy in the 1980s when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turner_Entertainment">Turner Entertainment</a> introduced <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_colorization">film colorization</a>.</p>

<p>Would the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auguste_and_Louis_Lumi%C3%A8re">Lumière Brothers</a> have opposed such manipulations of their film? Perhaps not—but that doesn’t mean we should do anything more than respectfully restore classic cinema. The documentary <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/lumiere-2016/">Lumière!</a></em> (2016) was a much more faithful approach, offering beautiful restorations. As for creative experimentation, it demonstrates that cinema can be changed in any way we can imagine.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>L’arrivée d’un train à La Ciotat</em> (1896)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0000012/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-arrival-of-a-train-at-la-ciotat/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Lumière!</em> (2016)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt5954462/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/lumiere-2016/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network">Artificial Neural Network</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepfake">Deepfake</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Film_colorization">Film Colorization</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motion_interpolation">Motion Interpolation</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turner_Entertainment">Turner Entertainment</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_scaler">Video Scaler</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="articles">Articles</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://gizmodo.com/neural-networks-upscale-film-from-1896-to-4k-make-it-l-1841449875">“Neural Networks Upscale Film from 1896 to 4K, Make It Look Like It Was Shot on a Modern Smartphone,” <em>Gizmodo</em></a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In with the Old]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Year of the Parasite</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/02/03/year-of-the-parasite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Year of the Parasite" /><published>2020-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/02/03/year-of-the-parasite</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/02/03/year-of-the-parasite.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="year-of-the-parasite">Year of the Parasite</h1>

<p><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/parasite-2019/"><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5e13b779a521ce05b02b31c9/1580677793362-NJRQCJT2ZG3BTGNCRGE2/Parasite_Comp.png" alt="Parasite_Comp.png" /></a></p>

<p>With the U.S. success of <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/parasite-2019/">기생충 (Parasite)</a></em>, distributor Neon released Bong Joon-ho’s <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/bong-joon-ho-black-white-parasite-cut-1274862">Black and White version</a> in Los Angeles and New York. This isn’t the first time a filmmaker has revisited a color film in black and white: <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/mad-max-fury-road/">Mad Max: Fury Road</a></em> (2015) and <em><a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-mist/">The Mist</a></em> (2007) both have black and white cuts that their directors consider the preferred versions. For <em>Parasite</em>, the switch to monochrome adds a layer of contrast to its already layered story.</p>

<p>We see the world in color, but films must be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_grading">color graded</a> to achieve the intended look. Shot by shot, the color correctionist ensures each scene looks right—originally through <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printer_point">printer points</a> and now via tools like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DaVinci_Resolve">DaVinci Resolve</a>. When creating a black and white version, desaturating requires further corrections to control contrast and tonal values.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0393240/">Kyung-pyo Hong</a></em>’s cinematography and <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm4342766/">Ha-jun Lee</a></em>’s production design brilliantly complement each other in <em>Parasite</em>, but in black and white, we notice subtle visual cues more vividly. Shadows reveal as much as highlights, and the differences between the two families become clearer in terms of lighting and tone.</p>

<p>A few years ago, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001752/">Steven Soderbergh</a> posted a desaturated version of <em>Raiders of the Lost Ark</em> (1981) on his website <a href="http://extension765.com/soderblogh/18-raiders">Extension 765</a> to study its staging. For me, that black and white version drew attention to <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0005878/">Douglas Slocombe</a>’s masterful cinematography and exposure, which is even more impressive if the stories are true that <a href="https://variety.com/2016/film/people-news/douglas-slocombe-dead-raiders-of-the-lost-ark-cinematographer-1201711843/">he never used a light meter</a>.</p>

<p>Similarly, <em>Parasite</em> in monochrome makes it easier to admire the craft and lighting choices. It’s an intriguing look for a film I consider the best of 2019.</p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<h4 id="films">Films</h4>

<ul>
  <li><em>Mad Max: Fury Road</em> (2015)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1392190/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/mad-max-fury-road/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>The Mist</em> (2007)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0884328/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/the-mist/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Parasite</em> (2019)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6751668/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/parasite-2019/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
  <li><em>Raiders of the Lost Ark</em> (1981)<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0082971/reference">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/raiders-of-the-lost-ark/">Letterboxd</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="people">People</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Douglas Slocombe<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0005878/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Slocombe">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Ha-jun Lee<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm4342766/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lee_Ha-jun">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Kyung-pyo Hong<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0393240/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong_Kyung-pyo">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
  <li>Steven Soderbergh<br />
[<a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001752/">IMDb</a> // <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Soderbergh">Wikipedia</a>]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="references">References</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_grading">Color Grading</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DaVinci_Resolve">DaVinci Resolve</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposure_latitude">Exposure Latitude</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_meter">Light Meter</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printer_point">Printer Point</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="articles">Articles</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/bong-joon-ho-black-white-parasite-cut-1274862">“Bong Joon Ho Talks Genesis of New Black-and-White <em>Parasite</em> Cut,” <em>Hollywood Reporter</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://variety.com/2016/film/people-news/douglas-slocombe-dead-raiders-of-the-lost-ark-cinematographer-1201711843/#!">“Douglas Slocombe, Cinematographer for ‘Raiders of the Lost Ark,’ Dies at 103,” <em>Variety</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiewire.com/2019/11/parasite-cinematographer-hong-kyung-pyo-1202189824/#!">“Parasite: Shooting Bong Joon Ho’s Social Thriller Through the Lens of Class Divide,” <em>IndieWire</em></a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="other">Other</h4>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://extension765.com/soderblogh/18-raiders">Extension 765: <em>Raiders</em></a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Year of the Parasite]]></summary></entry></feed>